[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the shorter note on nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: The opinion has been expressed in the PTS dictionary that nibbāna is not transcendental.
[SPEAKER_02]: If by transcendental is meant mystical, either in the sense of having to do with the supposed divine ground, or simply in the nature of a mystery, then nibbāna, or extinction, is not transcendental.
[SPEAKER_02]: Indeed, it is anti-transcendental.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or mystification is a state not of the arahant, who has realized nibbāna, but of the patujana, who has not.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, we talk about this often, like, you know, mystical kinds of thinking and how that's not correct to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: What exactly is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you clarify what makes a thought or a view mystical, as opposed to non-mystical or perhaps rational?
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, eh... means, what we spoke before, means assuming it outside of your experience, which in itself is something you can't even conceive, even as a theory.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which is why it's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, mysticism would be the counterpart of the equally external view of scientific projection of the public world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can either take it in that direction, direction of matter, when you say it's all just electrons and atoms and chemistry and whatnot, or you can take it in the other matter, but from the same point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: of that external... external to the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: You assume there is something outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You assume that you can assume the external.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence... hence it's mystical.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that usually is pretty much the... the very... the common thread in... in any or all of the mystical religions, no matter how different they might be on the particular manifestations of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a thread of a view underneath, it's that very thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Assuming the external entity, the external realm, the external... And that's when they say transcendental, that's usually what's meant by it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Along those same lines, he concludes that paragraph.
[SPEAKER_02]: When a fire becomes extinguished, we do not suppose that it enters a mysterious transcendental state.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is that prominent wrong view of people assuming
[SPEAKER_01]: Once the flame extinguishes, it kind of goes further.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, any notion of further means you assuming the possibility of a realm outside of this, the five aggregates, the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, that assumption is within the five aggregates, the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said, you cannot step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But far near, up or down, big or small, the five aggregates are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you remember the eons of previous lives, you remember within these five aggregates or one among them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the notion of external to it, it's already something that's being perceived.
[SPEAKER_01]: As such, it's already something that's thoroughly within the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's one of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of assuming the extinction of the flame, assuming the sort of the projection into some another realm of invisible, no matter how ambiguous, you still perceive it as such, which means it's a gratuitous assumption that you cannot actually experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of that, it's just the simile of the nibbāna being the extinguishing the flame, means exactly that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Extinguishing of the flame.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of fire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of burning,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no more now, where that absence gone, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Has gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: Later on in the note, he mentions how it can be thought of as transcendental in the sense of being outside the realm of rational investigation or the patujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: You transcend greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You transcend ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, it's transcendental within the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you cannot transcend the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why would you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as the Buddha said, upādāna is not the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they're not the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: desire and lust, indriya-vigārtha, five aggregates, the upādāna is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you transcending the five aggregates and finding some hidden realm, well, you'll be carrying your upādāna with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're trying to get rid of that which is not a problem, by mistaking it to be a problem.
It goes on to...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'd like to make some points about the word lokuttara itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: The first one mentioning how there's, you know, there's no particular reason why I am, why I exist.
[SPEAKER_02]: Hence, one can't rationally reason out an escape from it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was more interested in the second part which reads, I can assert my existence or I can deny it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in order to do either, I must exist.
[SPEAKER_02]: For it is I myself who assert or deny it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any attempt I make to abolish my existence tacitly confirms it.
[SPEAKER_01]: For it is my existence... That's what the existential philosophers meant when they said the existence precedes the essence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any essence you might have, it's given on the basis of existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you cannot rationalize
[SPEAKER_01]: Outside of your existence, because that's in itself the act of rationalization, is something within the existing experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is from footnote C. He's basically talking about the idea of how people try and find some positive hope in nibbāna somehow, even if they... even if the suttas say otherwise.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he says, the suttas are less accommodating
[SPEAKER_02]: See, eh, Majjhima... Majjhima Nikāya, for an account of the eternalist's unrelieved angst in the face of subjective non-being, upon hearing the Buddha's teaching of extinction, he apprehends annihilation, despairs, and falls, beating his breast into confusion, but not so the Arya-sāvaka.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so that was it again.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, because it's within the five aggregates as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because it's within the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, it's not the the hidden realm that's been obscured by some veil of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is within this experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a person can... and there are the sutras where the Buddha said that a person thinks, oh, I'm attending nibbāna, this nibbāna is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, with the wrong view, with the wrong attitude, with appropriation, he's actually having the experience of non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he recognizes it as the experience of non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion, but he doesn't enter it, as the Buddha would say, because, well, he's not free from greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that experience, the experience of absence of greed, aversion, delusion, is a real phenomenon, a negative phenomenon, but real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, those people would get the hint of that, but they would be terrified, because they would see it through the assumption of a degree of being, the degree of positivity that is necessary for their existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything less than positivity that they have assumed, which is upādāna, pañca, abhāva, basically,
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything less than that is going to be terrifying.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to bring in anxiety.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's going to bring in fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I mean by discerning the negative appearing as negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not trying to make it positive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not trying to overly assume it into positive.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're actually undoing your dependence upon a certain degree of a positivity of a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, if there is fear in the face of nibbāna, it's because your assumption of being is being contradicted now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you recognize that there are other things lower than the threshold of what you deem to be existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they're way out of your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Way out of your comfort zone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Way out of anything that you've been conceiving so far.
[SPEAKER_01]: Way out of my sense of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it just results in an instant dread.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nibbāna, really, it's eh... it's where... it's where death is for a pūtujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: If a pūtujana... that's why... that's why they would jump into conclusion, ah, that will kill us, that will destroy us.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because for pūtujana, death is that direction of not-mind, annihilation, out of my control.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's gonna affect this life within these five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, really, that's why many... mindfulness of death is one of the quickest ways of becoming an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, it can be a bit risky as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Later in the note, there's a quote from the Udāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: It reads, there is amongst the non-born, non-become, non-made, non-determined.
[SPEAKER_02]: For if there were not that non-born, non-become, non-made, non-determined, an escape here from born, become, made, determined, would not be manifest.
[SPEAKER_02]: And also, from the Asaṅgata Samhita, destruction monks of lust, hate, delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: This, monks, is called the non-determined.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, it seems that whenever we talk about nirvana, it's always kind of given in these negative terms, like an absence, a non-something.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, is... is there some positive thing we can think of as nibbāna, or is it... Well, that absence is positive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Positive in its absence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence, it's a... it's a... it's a manifested phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as such, from that point of view, it is a positive thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not a positive thing in a sense of becoming an object of your senses, for example, which is usually what people regard as a positive thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why... that's why, I mean, you need to learn how to allow things, thoughts, feelings, perceptions to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just fall into kind of explaining them, or trying to get rid of them, or sort of rationalize them.
[SPEAKER_01]: By allowing things to endure, you see them that they exist on their own accord, they persist on their own accord.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by being able to do that, you will see that absences persist on their own accord.
[SPEAKER_01]: Negative presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why nibbāna would equate to the extinguishing of that indications caused by consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: The non-indicative consciousness has never been translated.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, negative exists as negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people usually associate or conflate existence with the positive, or with the degrees of positive, which is the degrees of bhava, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm doing the bhava, which clarifies the correct way of appearing negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the positive aspects of negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's when nibbāna is dhamma, but it's the asankhata dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the dhamma that you experience through extinguishing determinations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Determinations of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the absence of that which used to be a burning fire is a real experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: He says,
[SPEAKER_02]: But if in our stewing minds we still can't help feeling that nibbāna really ought somehow to be some eternity of positive enjoyment, or at least of experience, we may ponder these two sutta passages.
[SPEAKER_02]: The first one says,
[SPEAKER_02]: There are, monk, these three feelings stated by me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Pleasant feeling, unpleasant feeling, neither unpleasant nor pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: These three feelings have been stated by me.
[SPEAKER_02]: But this, monk, has been stated by me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever is felt counts as unpleasure, suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: That, however, monk, was said by me concerning the impermanence of determinations.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, the Venerable Sariputta said this.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is extinction, friends, that is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: This was said, the Venerable Udayi said to the Venerable Sariputta, that what herein is pleasant, friend Sariputta, since herein there is nothing felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just this is pleasant, friend, that herein there is nothing felt.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, these two suttas seem to be trying to point at the idea of what nibbāna is in regards to feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the first bit talks about from the point of view of Kutujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: The other one talks from the point of view of an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from the point of view of Kutujana, who still has craving in regard to pleasure, craving in regard to avoiding pain, that in order to overcome that, he needs to regard any arising of feeling as affected by craving, any arising of feeling as a problem, any arising of feeling as arising of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a problem, there is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why whatever it's felt counts as unpleasurable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because with that kind of attitude, he will then withdraw from... withdraw the notion of ownership of his own feelings and the notion of ownership of control.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the impermanence of the determinations.
[SPEAKER_01]: The determination for craving is the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, seeing that these feelings are anicca,
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot be owned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Will then result in fading away of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: From the point of view of Arahant, the fact that none of the feelings can affect him, and he has fully understood that, and fully experienced it, and fully verified it, that in itself is very pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that he doesn't feel anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is very agreeable.